George Rowen Papers
George Rowen Papers
1941-1963
Rowen, George.
14 linear ft.
Papers of the American photographer, contains clippings, negatives, 16mm film, prints, printed material, and personal papers.
149554
Biographical History
George Rowen was an American commercial and United Nations photographer. He worked as photographer and assistant photo editor for Austrian Illustrated News in Vienna while attending school (1937-1938). In the early 1940s he did publicity and freelance new photography in Chicago. He was inducted into the Army during World War II where he served as photographer for the Public Relations Office at Fort Benning, Georgia, and then was sent overseas with the 12th Army Group, Psychological Warfare Division as chief photographer. After being discharged from the Army in 1945 he was asked to remain in Europe to work for the War Department's newly created Publishing Operations Branch, Information Control Division, as editor and chief of the photo section. Upon returning to the United States in 1948 he was appointed Public Information Officer of the International Refugee Organization (IRO), an agency of the United Nations. When the IRO was eventually disbanded, he worked for several other agencies within the UN.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The George Rowen Papers contains clippings, 16mm film, negatives, personal papers, and prints. Many of the negatives are not identified other than by number. Notable persons and events represented in the photographs and negatives include General Dwight D. Eisenhower in Munich, Josef Goebbels' sister, King Hussein of Jordan, Thor Heyerdahl, Mrs. Rudolf Hess, the Nuremberg Trials, Charlie Chaplin, and the 1948 Winter Olympics in St. Moritz. The collection also includes two copies of a film made by the International Refugee Organization (IRO), intended as orientation films for displaced persons (refugees).
Arrangement of the Collection
Each series is arranged alphabetically.
Related Material
has the papers of many noted photographers and photojournalists, including Margaret Bourke-White. Please refer to for a complete listing.
Subject and Genre Headings
Photography; Browder, Earl, 1891-1973 -- Photographs.; Chaplin, Charlie -- Photographs.; Dietrich, Sepp, 1892-1966 -- Photographs.; Eisenhower, Dwight D. (Dwight David), 1890-1969 -- Photographs.; Heyerdahl, Thor -- Photographs.; La Guardia, Fiorello H. (Fiorello Henry), 1882-1947 -- Photographs.; Luce, Clare Boothe, 1903-1987 -- Photographs.; Rowen, George.; Allied Forces. -- Supreme Headquarters. -- Psychological Warfare Division.; International Refugee Organization -- Photographs.; Radio Luxembourg.; United Nations -- Photograph collections.; United Nations. -- General Assembly -- Photographs.; United States. -- Office of War Information.; Commercial photography.; Nuremberg War Crime Trials, Nuremberg, Germany, 1946-1949 -- Photographs.; Olympic Winter Games (5th: 1948: Saint Moritz, Switzerland) -- Photographs.; Photographers -- United States.; Photography -- Films.; Advertising photography.; Soldiers -- Photographs.; Travel photography.; Chicago (Ill.) -- Photographs.; France -- Photographs.; Germany -- Photographs.; Italy -- Photographs.; Mexico -- Photographs.; 16mm (photographic film size); Clippings (information artifacts); Negatives (photographs); Photographs.; Photographers.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Inventory
- Clippings
  - Miscellaneous, 1941-1963; 7 folders (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous, 1941-1963; 2 folders (Box 2)
- Films
  - Journey to Your New Home (International Refugee Organization [IRO] Orientation No. 2), undated; can labeled "Orientation Film for DP’s Regarding Shipboard Life”; rowen_g_001; 16mm film, 1 reel (Oversize 1)
  - Journey to Your New Home (International Refugee Organization [IRO] Orientation No. 2), undated; rowen_g_002; duplicate of rowen_g_001; 16mm film, 1 reel (Oversize 1)
- Negatives
  - 35 mm negatives, unnumbered
    - Miscellaneous, 8 folders (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous, 7 folders (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous, 8 folders (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous, 7 folders (Box 6)
    - Miscellaneous, 7 folders (Box 7)
    - Miscellaneous, 6 folders (Box 8)
  - Medium (6cm by 6cm) and large (4"x5") format negatives, numbered, Numbering is not always consecutive, there are gaps in the sequence. This is the first of two numbered sequences (see below for the second).
    - Negatives 33-1499 (Box 9)
    - Negatives 1500-4099 (Box 10)
    - Negatives 4100-4849 (Box 11)
    - Negatives 4850-5559 (Box 12)
    - Negatives 5560-5710 (Box 13)
  - Medium (6cm by 6cm) and large size (4"x5") negatives, people and places, People are listed alphabetically, followed by places
    - Allied Syndicate, 2 envelopes, one with 2 indecipherable names (Box 13)
    - Ash, Harry-Dorothy-Fredy Seneca Hotel, [Chicago], 1942; 2 envelopes (Box 13)
    - Baierl, Lotte (aka Mrs. Lotte Hass) (Box 13)
    - Bemelmans, Ludwig, writer, etc., author of the Madeleine children's books (Box 13)
    - Benatzky, Ralph (Dr.) [in same envelope as Else Kaufmann], 1/23/1943 (Box 13)
    - Berger, Dave, Voice of America (Box 13)
    - Bienstock, Freddie, 1950; with Lucille Gordon (Box 13)
    - Boothe Luce, Claire, Cologne, 1945; mis-written on envelope as "Claire Luce Boot" (Box 13)
    - Brandt, Otto (Box 13)
    - Braun, Harald (Dr.) (Box 13)
    - Bridges, Henry Styles, U.S. Senator; pictured with Sen. Saltonstall (Box 13)
    - Bronstein, Paula, 1951 (Box 13)
    - Browder, Earl, 10/26/1942 (Box 13)
    - Byrnes, James F., U.S. Secretary of State from 1945 to 1947; 2 envelopes, "Byrnes in Munich" and "Byrnes in Stuttgart" (Box 13)
    - Chaplin, Charlie, 10/14/1942 (Box 13)
    - Charlotte, Grand Duchess of Luxembourg (Box 13)
    - Dickey, Colonel, wedding at Fort Benning, Georgia (Box 13)
    - Dietrich, Josef "Sepp," Mrs. [Moninger-Brenner, Ursula], appears in photo with Sigurd (Sigi) Hinrichsen (Mrs. Joachim Peiper) at Malmedy massacre trial in Dachau; her husband Josef "Sepp" Dietrich was general in the Waffen-SS (Box 13)
    - von Dittmar, Kurt, German general (Box 13)
    - Donath, John, 4/30/1942; 2 envelopes (Box 13)
    - Eisenhower, Dwight D. General in Munich, 2 envelopes (Box 13)
    - von Epp, Ritter (Box 13)
    - Friends [of George Rowen, presumably] (Box 13)
    - Goebbels, "sister" written on envelope, presumably sister of Josef Goebbels (Box 13)
    - Gordon, Lucille with Freddie Bienstock, 1950 (Box 13)
    - Grinde, J., fellow UN photographer; 2 envelopes (Box 13)
    - Hass, Hans, famous deep-sea diver, pictured with wife Lotte, misspelled “Lottie” on envelope (Box 13)
    - Hass, Lotte, aka Lotte Baierl, second wife of Hans Hass (Box 13)
    - Hess, Mrs. Rudolf, 1945; aka Ilse Pröhl (Box 13)
    - Heyerdahl, Thor (Box 13)
    - Hoffmann, Heinrich, Spruchkammer trial (Box 13)
    - Hussein, King of Jordan (Box 13)
    - Johnston, Nov 1950 (Box 13)
    - Justh, Moric (Box 13)
    - Kallmann, Hans J., German artist (Box 13)
    - Kaufmann, Else, 1/23/1943; pictured in same envelope as Dr. Ralph Benatzky (Box 13)
    - Klein, Peter, 1/22/1943 (Box 13)
    - Kreisler, Fritz, 1/20/1943; Austrian-born violinist; taken at Orchestra Hall, most likely Chicago (Box 13)
    - Kreuzberg, Harald (Box 13)
    - Kwok, Nov 1955 (Box 13)
    - Kuhn, Fritz, 1947; "ex-Bund leader" on envelope (Box 13)
    - La Guardia, Fiorello in Munich, well-known Mayor of New York City (Box 13)
    - Lehn family (Box 13)
    - Leopoldi, Hermann at Orchestra Hall [Chicago], 10/10/1942; Austrian composer and musician (Box 13)
    - Loewenstein, Charlie (Box 13)
    - Luckmayer, Karl (Box 13)
    - Lustfield, Betty Joan, 5/24/1942; 1/18/1943; 2 envelopes (Box 13)
    - Lustfield, Charles (Box 13)
    - McGrath [family], 12/06/1942 (Box 13)
    - Morse, Wayne [Lyman], Senator from Oregon (Box 13)
    - Mother [presumably George Rowen's], 3 envelopes (Box 13)
    - MRBC [Multi-Role Bridge Company), 50th, soldiers (Box 13)
    - Nancy [no surname] (Box 13)
    - Moninger-Brenner, Ursula, Mrs. Josef "Sepp" Dietrich; her husband Josef "Sepp" Dietrich was a general in the Waffen-SS; appears in same photo with Sigurd (Sigi) Hinrichsen (Mrs. Joachim Peiper) at Malmedy massacre trial in Dachau (Box 13)
    - P—, Lilian [last name illegible] (Box 13)
    - Peiper, Joachim Mrs., aka Sigurd "Sigi" Hinrichsen (Box 13)
    - von Popen, Ernst, labeled "General," wearing German uniform; possibly meant to be Franz von Papen? (Box 13)
    - Reijmers, B— [first name illegible] (Box 13)
    - Reiman, Henry (Box 13)
    - R—gold, Olin [last name only partly legible], 1956 (Box 13)
    - Robeson, Paul at Orchestra Hall [Chicago], 11/17/1942; American singer and activist (Box 13)
    - Russian Army, portraits of soldiers (Box 13)
    - Saltonstall, Leverett A., U.S. Senator, pictured with Senator Bridges (Box 13)
    - Schwarzkopf, Ruth (Box 13)
    - Shapiro-Landau wedding, 8/16/1942 (Box 13)
    - Sl—, Marcella [last name illegible], IRO, 1950 (Box 13)
    - Stadler (family), 9/7/1942 (Box 13)
    - Stedman, Seymour, 11/20/1942 (Box 13)
    - Thiele, Rolf (Box 13)
    - Tillinger (Box 13)
    - UNCA [United Nations Correspondents Association], 1955 (Box 13)
    - Weiss, Claire (Box 13)
    - Miscellaneous unidentified people (or unreadable names) in envelopes and separately (Box 14)
    - Austria: Salzburg Festival, 1948 (Box 14)
    - Austria: Vienna, 2 envelopes (Box 14)
    - Camp Sharpe [near Gettysburg, Pennsylvania], 1944 (Box 14)
    - Chicago: Chicago Cathedral, 12/24/1942 (Box 14)
    - Chicago: Chicago Opera Company, 10/22/1942 (Box 14)
    - Chicago: Chicago Service Men Center, 6/6/1942 (Box 14)
    - Chicago: Cuter Squash Club, 1328 E. 55th St., 8/30/1942 (Box 14)
    - Chicago: Defense Bond Sales at Marshall Field, 4/18/1942 (Box 14)
    - Chicago: Defense Bond Sale Parade, 5/2/1942 (Box 14)
    - Chicago: Easter Parade, 4/5/1942 (Box 14)
    - Chicago: Fire, 2 envelopes (Box 14)
    - Chicago: Hollywood Victory Campaign, 5/6/1942 (Box 14)
    - Chicago: Mandel’s Fashion Show College Shop, 8/12/1942 (Box 14)
    - Chicago: Navy Day Parade, 10/27/1942 (Box 14)
    - Chicago: O.C.D. [Office of Civilian Defense], 11/2/1942 (Box 14)
    - Chicago: Street Condition, 5/27/1942 (Box 14)
    - France: Paris, 5 envelopes (Box 14)
    - Germany: Bavarian Parliament, 2 envelopes (Box 14)
    - Germany: Berlin, 2 envelopes (Box 14)
    - Germany: Berchtesgaden (Box 14)
    - Germany: Buchenwald Trial (Box 14)
    - Germany: Cologne, 1945 (Box 14)
    - Germany: Frankfurt, 1946 celebration, 2 envelopes (Box 14)
    - Germany: Frankfurt, 1948 celebration, 4 envelopes (Box 14)
    - Germany: Frankfurt, Paul's Church (Box 14)
    - Germany: Moosburg Internment Camp (Box 14)
    - Germany: Munich (Box 14)
    - Germany: Munich Synagogue (Box 14)
    - Germany: Munich Theater Club (Box 14)
    - Germany: Nurnberg Trial, 5 envelopes (Box 14)
    - Germany: Richard Wagner Monument (Box 14)
    - Germany: Stuttgart (Box 14)
    - Germany: Tengernsee Celebration (Box 14)
    - Germany, unspecified, post-war (Box 14)
    - Italy: Lugano (Box 15)
    - Italy: Milano Fair, 1948; 2 envelopes (Box 15)
    - Italy: Milano May Day Celebration, 1948 (Box 15)
    - Italy: Mille Miglia, 1948 (Box 15)
    - Italy: Verona (Box 15)
    - Luxembourg: HABE personnel (Box 15)
    - Luxembourg: Luxemburg Personnel (Box 15)
    - Luxembourg: Psychological Warfare Division (PWD)/Supreme Headquarters Allied Expeditionary Force (SHAEF) office and personnel, mis-written as "SHAEL" on envelope (Box 15)
    - Luxembourg: PWD activities (Box 15)
    - New York City (Box 15)
    - New York City: "Grille for Allied Syndicate", 1949; the yacht of Adolf Hitler, the Grille, arrives in New York Harbor, with letter explaining who is on board for a publicity shot (Box 15)
    - Prague (Box 15)
    - Publishing Operation Branch, 4 envelopes, unspecified location (Box 15)
    - Security Council (Box 15)
    - Switzerland: Arosa (Box 15)
    - Switzerland: Zurich, 2 envelopes (Box 15)
    - Switzerland: Olympic Games in St. Moritz, 1948 (Box 15)
    - UNICEF (Box 15)
    - United Nations Correspondents Dinner (Box 15)
    - U.S. Army, 9/12/1942; location unspecified, appears to be training exercises (Box 15)
    - U.S. Airlines lobby (Box 15)
  - Medium (6cm by 6cm) and large size (4"x5") negatives, miscellaneous, Numbering is not always consecutive, there are gaps in the sequence. This is the second of two numbered sequences (see above for the first).
    - Miscellaneous, unnumbered and unlabeled, in envelopes, 2 folders (Box 15)
    - Negatives 400-599, 2 folders (Box 15)
    - Negatives 600-2499, 10 folders (Box 16)
    - Negatives 2500-3199, 10 folders (Box 17)
    - Negatives 3200-3599, 4 folders (Box 18)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Medium (6cm by 6cm) and large (4"x5") format negatives, unidentified, unnumbered, not in envelopes (Box 18)
    - Glass plate negatives, 2 items (Box 18)
- Personal papers
  - Antique car show (Box 2)
  - Brazil (Box 2)
  - Cartoons (Box 2)
  - Correspondence (Box 2)
  - Equipment (Box 2)
  - Expenses (Box 2)
  - Fragments (Box 2)
  - Haiti (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - Notes (Box 2)
  - Official documents (Box 2)
  - Publications, various, 2 folders (Box 18)
  - Publications, various (Box 19)
  - Publications, various (Oversize 2)
  - Resume (Box 2)
  - United Nations (Box 2)
  - Vacation (Box 2)
- Prints
  - Advertising (Box 19)
  - Autos, 3 folders (Box 19)
  - Ballet, 2 folders (Box 19)
  - Ballet (cont.), 2 folders (Box 20)
  - Boating, 3 folders (Box 20)
  - Brazil (Box 20)
  - Europe (Box 20)
  - Europe (cont.), 8 folders (Box 21)
  - Europe (cont.), 2 folders (Box 22)
  - Family, 2 folders (Box 22)
  - Far East (Box 22)
  - Hobbies, 2 folders (Box 22)
  - Immigrants (Box 22)
  - Mexico, 4 folders (Box 23)
  - Military, 2 folders (Box 23)
  - Miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 23)
  - Miscellaneous (cont.) (Box 24)
  - Miscellaneous oversize (Oversize 2)
  - Office of War Information (Box 24)
  - Pets (Box 24)
  - Radio Luxembourg (Box 24)
  - Schoolchildren (Box 24)
  - United Nations, 2 folders (Box 24)
  - United Nations, 7 folders (Box 25)
  - United Nations, 6 folders (Box 26)
  - Woman model (Box 26)